hey folks Aaron Scott here so Daylight
Savings Time ends this weekend which
means we get an extra hour of sleep this
Sunday at 2 A.M but it is an hour that
we lost earlier in the year in March and
of course people have strong feelings
about this whether we should change the
time at all and in which direction the
US government has even taken up the
issue and a big question in this
daylight savings debate is how it
affects People's Health so we talked to
health correspondent Allison Aubry this
past spring to get some answers
you're listening to shortwave
from NPR
so much of life is about trade-offs you
give a little you get a little and we've
got a trade-off today that I sure have
thoughts on maybe you do too what about
you Allison Aubry yes I've got some
thoughts okay we're talking dear
listeners about the twice yearly
changing of the clocks spring forward
when Daylight Saving Time begins and
fall backward when it ends it may not
sound like a big deal but it turns out
our bodies are a lot more sensitive to
time than most of us ever realized and
back in 2015 I spoke to the Circadian
scientist named Fred Turek at
Northwestern University about it yeah
let's listen to some of that we've known
for a long time about the Master Clock
in our brains that synchronizes our body
to the 24-hour light dark cycle but in
recent years scientists have made a
pretty cool Discovery it turns out that
we have different clocks in every organ
yes there are clocks in all the cells of
your body wow it's kind of stunning yes
that is a discovery that's literally
surprised us I must say Turek says think
of all these clocks in our bodies as
instruments or players in an orchestra
the idea that the heart has a clock
think of it as a drum
and the kidneys the kidneys have a clock
two clocks one in each kidney maybe
they're the horns
then there's the pancreas oh yes the
pancreas has a clock that's the flute
foreign
s is like the Symphony conductor keeping
all of the players in sync
once the conductor comes on everybody's
in synchrony and it sounds beautiful
the idea that your body is functionally
normally when everybody's in synchrony
with the master conductor in your brain
you're sleeping well eating regularly
and feeling good but what if the clocks
get out of sync
it sounds so bad right ah The Clash the
cacophony yeah cacophony that's that's
how I feel uh daylight saving time it's
kind of like oh you're just all over the
place and that really takes us to
today's debate that if we do away with
switching the clock twice a year which
many scientists say would be a good idea
the debate is which one is better having
extra sunlight in the morning or the
evening yeah and in a rare bipartisan
moment the U.S Senate voted unanimously
earlier this month to make Daylight
Saving Time permanent some states have
already opted out of the twice annual
clock Change most of Arizona and the
state of Hawaii for instance remain on
Standard Time year round
for any change to permanently do away
with the clocks changing around the
country though the House of
Representatives would need to pass the
measure too and while this year the bill
is not likely to become law more than
ever the discussions seem to be out
there so today on the show to keep or
not to keep or what to keep does the U.S
abandon the clock changing and if so
what does the science say about whether
the country adopts permanent daylight
saving time or year-round Standard time
you're listening to shortwave the daily
science podcast from NPR
foreign
it was only two weeks ago that we set
our clocks forward an hour
and I had to like remember which buttons
to push on the microwave to make it
happen but you know unless you went to
bed an hour early most of us lost an
hour of sleep it's kind of tedious but
having our bodies adjusted by now you
would think that it wouldn't be a big
deal to adjust to a one hour change in
time in this instance losing an hour
basically having a 23 hour day once a
year but our body's gonna tell a
different story I mean what's surprising
is that the springtime clock Change is
actually linked to an increased risk of
heart attacks and other cardiac events
huh and I talked to a Cardiologist his
name is Jay chudow at Montefiore Health
who was actually documented this
phenomenon he compared Hospital
admissions for a type of heart
arrhythmia or irregular heartbeat called
atrial fibrillation in the days after
the spring time change compared to the
rest of the year we found that there
were more hospitalizations for atrial
fibrillation after the spring time
change I was very surprised because it's
just one hour change why should it cause
this large effect he says people who
ended up in the hospital with afib as
it's referred to had other risk factors
too these weren't young healthy people
so the time change wasn't the sole cause
of their event but likely the factor
that put them over the edge so why does
this happen do scientists know exactly
why isn't nailed down yet but what has
become clear is that our bodies are
super sensitive to time as we just heard
above a few years back three scientists
actually won a Nobel Prize for their
work that helped made that discovery
that we have clocks running in every
organ and every cell of our body and
that we're just orchestral beings
literally time keeping machines that's
right it's one way to look at it I mean
and it really the analogy really does
hold up I mean the first rays of light
each morning helps to reset our clocks
each day and with that abrupt change
that 23 hour day when we Spring Forward
it can disrupt our internal clocks in
ways that can be harmful in addition
think about this Emily when much of the
nation is tired and groggy on a single
day from yeah collectively losing an
hour of sleep it can lead to a lot of
distracted drivers on the road traffic
accidents after the time change there's
definitely a signal that there's more of
those after we change the clocks just
like there are more workplace accidents
and such and if I can make my own
admission I was involved in an incident
on the Wednesday after the time change
last week he collided with another car I
don't have all the details but it was
not his fault and Emily this may seem
like a coincidence but it turns out I
was also involved in a traffic incident
the day of the spring forward change oh
no are you okay I am completely fine
what happened is I actually backed into
to my neighbor's Tesla he was not in his
usual parking space I was in a hurry
running late and boom it was just easy
to do I didn't look in the rearview
mirror thousands of dollars later
questioning why this happened I decided
to reach out to the Circadian medicine
clinic at Northwestern I spoke to Dr
Sabra Abbott she's a neurologist by
training and her research focuses on
understanding the impacts of timing on
our health can you claim daylight
savings time is to blame probably
um I don't know if that would hold
import but you probably were sleep
deprived you were probably a little
misaligned and I think that probably
played a role in that now thankfully no
one was hurt in my fender bender which
is the most important thing but one
study from 2020 found a six percent rise
in fatal car crashes after the spring
time change wow you know the date is a
little bit mixed on this some studies
point to higher risks of accidents in
the morning during daylight savings
months due to the darkness in the
morning it can kind of go both ways but
Abbott says what is very clear is that
there are negative health effects linked
to Shifting the clocks this is
fascinating to me and and you know it's
tough to determine causality here like
she's saying but part of the scientific
process is stepping back from Individual
experiences and looking at Broad Trends
and if you're saying that health and
safety kind of Trend in a bad Direction
around this time of year because of the
clock Change
what is the conversation like about
doing away with it entirely and just
just keeping to one time in the US I
think there's a lot of support for that
um there's support among politicians
among some scientists support among
people who are just annoyed by the time
change but I think the big question
becomes which time should become
permanent should we adopt Standard Time
year round with more sunlight in the
morning or permanently adopt a Daylight
Saving Time with more sunlight in the
early evening as the Senate has voted to
do well if the early race of the sun
reset a human clock wouldn't daylight
saving time
kind of misaligned with our natural
rhythms well that's exactly the concern
and Dr Abbott says a lot of sleep
scientists think that the Senate got it
wrong one of the consequences of
permanent daylight savings time is
actually that you end up finding it
harder to fall asleep at night because
you're getting that light later in night
when it actually pushes time later and
you're getting less of that light in the
morning which makes it harder to wake up
in the morning in fact the American
Academy of sleep medicine has a position
paper on this in favor of moving to
permanent Standard Time so more light in
the morning Yeah it's you're trying to
like align what's happening in the
environment with the clock in a person's
body so if sleep doctors mostly prefer
permanent Standard Time why did the
Senate choose the other direction why
did they go for like a permanent
daylight saving time yeah I think to
answer that you have to go way back when
daylight saving time was first
introduced as a concept about a hundred
years ago the idea back then is that it
would save energy if people need it less
power to heat their homes in the evening
there'd be some Energy Efficiency but
it's not clear that this Energy
Efficiency has really ever panned out
the argument today that's more relevant
I think is that more sunlight in the
afternoon makes it easier for people to
go out and do things after work and
spend more money doing it I spoke to
Lyle Beckwith he's with the National
Association of convenience stores and
that group actually lobbied way back in
the 1980s to extend daylight saving time
for a longer stretch of the year for
this very reason when people come home
from work and there's more Daylight they
tend to be more active they go to
sporting events they play softball they
golf They barbecue and that translates
into an increase in sales of people
coming in to buy more water more
Gatorade more beer more charcoal more
everything they don't have specific
numbers on this but he says stores tell
him that they see a 15 to 20 percent
boost in sales at this time of year yeah
I'm guilty of this I'd be in that data
but you know this is just like human
health colliding with kind of economic
health it's a story that is classic and
you said though it's unlikely such a
change will become federal law this year
even if the conversation has been
stewing for a long time you know I think
Congress may end up giving up on the
measure this year because let's just
face it there are lots of high priority
issues right now there's Ukraine and
inflation
um I mean in the House of
Representatives does not have a plan at
the moment to vote on it though it is
worth noting that it passed the Senate
by unanimous consent meaning no one
objected to it there was no actual roll
call vote uh so it does have some
momentum and if Congress did act many
retailers say they would rather see
permanent minute daylight saving time so
the question is like where does that
leave all of us right as a human being I
mean where I've kind of landed is I get
it that you know Standard Time with more
light in the morning is probably what
our natural rhythms are craving however
you know as a person who works during
the day I also like the idea of being
able to like play tennis or meet people
in the afternoon after work and it's
still light so in a way we're kind of
living this compromise you know yeah so
I guess I'll see you at the 7-Eleven
picking up charcoal for the time being
all right you're inviting me over for a
barbecue is that right yeah I have that
right
thanks Allison thank you this episode
was produced by Thomas Liu edited by
Jane greenhalsh and Gisele Grayson and
backtracked by Catherine Seifer Gisele
Grayson is our senior supervising editor
Andrea kissick is the head of the
science desk Edith Chapin is the
executive editor and vice president of
news and Nancy Barnes is our senior vice
president of news I'm Emily Kwong I'm
Allison Aubry thank you for listening to
shortwave the daily science podcast from
NPR
thank you