you're listening to shortwave
from NPR
the nervous one is close by but one
second
oh can you mail again
Katie Woo is a cat person she has twin
Tabby Brothers Calvin and Hobbes the
meowing you heard came from Hobbs Hobbs
is a zoom Enthusiast but a nothing else
Enthusiast he is afraid of food
human beings other cats heavy steps
vacuum cleaners wind and foil he likes
having his teeth rubbed so I'm doing
that to calm him down Katie loves her
boys but she wasn't always a feline
mother of two in fact this wasn't a
situation she ever saw herself in it all
if we put me 10 years ago into this
exact room it would be a catastrophe
tell us about it what would happen oh I
missed that pun
[Music]
[Laughter]
okay okay yeah so basically for the
first I'd say 20 years of my life I was
I wouldn't say deathly allergic to cats
but whatever is one tear below deathly
allergic to cats miserably I'd walk into
a room either where there were cats or
where cats had recently been or as
distantly as months ago and my body
could tell uh my eyes would start
watering my nose would immediately clog
up I would feel my throat tighten it's
possible for Katie it was genetic it
happened to my mom too my siblings have
it it's like this was my destiny or so
she thought because sometime between the
end of college and grad school I was
suddenly able to be around cats and
nothing would happen Kitty remembers
that around this time she even went with
a friend to help them adopt a dog they
hung out in the shelter for hours there
were rows and rows of cats in a facility
full of dander and cat hair and other
cat remnants and she was completely fine
I did not know what was going on so
after that I sort of decided to test it
out more and more and more and just it
kept being the case that nothing would
happen people can outgrow allergies but
it seems less common to have the kind of
complete night and day change the Katie
experienced so either this is the
longest fever dream ever
or something in my body changed that
just decided you know one day your
immune system is terrified of cats
and then it got over it so today on the
show we talked to Katie Wu about the
complex world of allergies why they may
happen and what might cause them to
change turning even the most catallergic
into the cat obsessed do you want to
meow can you meow into a report it
I'm Aaron Scott brand new dog owner of
Oliver serif Scott lamb and you're
listening to shortwave the daily science
podcast from NPR
foreign
[Music]
love pets feline and otherwise we love
snuggling them and we love producing
stories about them and if you want to
help us create more Animal Kingdom
content then sign up for NPR plus it
means you get the show ad free and
you're contributing to our ability to
unlock feline Mysteries if you're
already a subscriber thank you thank you
thank you find out more at
plus.npr.org shortwave
[Music]
foreign
let's dive into the biology of allergies
you write that they're basically like
little molecular screw-ups what do you
mean by that yeah so I mean think about
the things that people tend to be
allergic to peanuts pollen shellfish for
most people these are harmless things
and they should be harmless things but
the sort of classic version of this is
you're exposed to something a couple
times usually early in life there are
some exceptions to that you know maybe
the first time the body sees it and goes
huh something about this doesn't sit
right with me some sort of response
develops and the next time that same
allergen comes around the body's like
oh no the last time I saw this I got
really nervous and now I am giving like
a full-blown freak out Katie says there
are basically two parts to an allergic
reaction
[Music]
step one is your body has to First
recognize the thing as something that
just raises it tackles it's called
sensitization something triggers a
hypersensitivity in the immune system
and then those crazy symptoms are the
actual allergic response so what's like
detection reaction so when people's
bodies overreact to them you know they
get hives or they go into anaphylactic
shock they stop being able to breathe
like some people can even die from these
reactions these are basically overblown
reactions to something that really
should be harmless
from what you write that really
surprised me is it's not just one
biological process it's complicated it's
particular to the allergen it differs
from person to person
tell us a little bit about what we're
learning about how complex it is it's
not like you can simply look at someone
or even look at their reaction to an
allergen and say oh I know exactly
what's happening molecularly in your
body which makes it really difficult to
say I have a good plan for treating you
or making these symptoms better you know
the general way that people approach
this and the most common way that people
approach this for a long time was to
give people antihistamines which is
basically treating a symptom of the
allergy but it's not really tackling it
at the source it's not teaching the body
hey chill out this thing that you're
scared of is actually benign it's really
just saying let's make you feel better
after your body starts reacting and so
you know a lot of this is like happening
kind of Downstream of the big problem
itself because that can happen in so
many ways and it's also not like
allergies can manifest in the same way
like think of anyone you know who has
seasonal allergies hay fever they sneeze
a ton when they have pollen
um and then compare that to someone and
who is allergic to peanuts and is going
into anaphylactic shock in a restaurant
those things look so different you write
that the world is becoming a more
allergic place that in America alone
there's about 50 million people who
experience allergies do scientists have
a sense of why this is
I think we have become a very super
clean Society especially in the western
world and kind of ironically like you
would think that leads to people getting
less sick but that also means we're not
exposing kids to a lot of the really
good microbes that are helping train
little kids bodies to distinguish good
from bad and so as dietary practices
have changed as we're you know using
tons and tons of antibiotics there are
some thoughts about you know how the
differences of modern childhood are
making it easier for bodies to basically
get confused about what does and doesn't
belong inside of them and do you have
any sense of how much it's an actual
rise in allergies versus an artifact of
you know people are looking for them
more and that it's it's more a rise in
reporting or a diagnosis yeah that's a
fantastic question and you know to be
totally honest there is a little bit of
both going on but even studies that have
sort of tried to account for the rise in
diagnosis and awareness and just of
parents coming in and being very worried
about this specific thing there does
seem to be a rise in this
um I think any allergist you talk to you
you'll ask them is are kids more
allergic than they were a few decades
ago and generally the answer I've gotten
is oh yeah
um it's definitely a thing but that said
there is definitely an over-diagnosis
problem with some allergies penicillin
is an amazing example uh apparently 90
of people who have penicillin allergy in
their medical chart don't actually have
a penicillin allergy and this is a huge
problem with drug allergies not just
because there's erroneous information in
those drug charts but because it limits
the options that people can get when
they get a bacterial infection Kitty
what are the ramifications for public
health of having this increasingly
allergic Planet this is absolutely I
think becoming a bigger issue because
even above and beyond the fact that
allergies can be a debilitating thing to
live with and it is costing a lot of
money and resources to figure out how to
improve these people's quality of life
and find adequate treatments for them
and to just better understand this
growing phenomenon I think it is
indicative that we don't fully
understand just fundamental aspects of
the immune system if allergies are
increasing I think that sort of also
speaks to
are we putting our kids in the best
environment should we be taking a closer
look at childhood should we be taking a
closer look at built environments should
we be taking a closer look at say our
early relationships with animals or
other humans and like if there are race
or socioeconomic disparities why might
those be so it's kind of both like an
effect and a symptom of a bigger problem
that is definitely worth examining
Katie's one of the lucky anomalies who
managed to kick her cat allergy but
allergies change in people all the time
they wax and they Wane and while
researchers don't always know what
determines all of these immune changes
there are some scientific explanations
basically this is called tolerance after
you develop analogy you can lose it by
growing tolerant the antigen your body
learns over time almost like the immune
system version of exposure therapy and
this is the principle behind allergy
shots right but it's complicated they
don't always work because people's
immune systems are are very weird and
sometimes people just grow out of their
allergies without a super clear
explanation I had no obvious
intervention
um so I am just sort of chalking it up
to the weirdness of immune systems being
sort of sensitive to all sorts of change
over time like how we're sleeping how
we're eating what's inside of our guts
bacteria wise
um where we live how old we are uh maybe
just the right combination of factors
happened for me at the right time the
hope is is scientists further unlock the
mysteries of allergies in our immune
systems they'll have more tools to go
about treating them I think there are
definitely people who were talking about
like gene therapy and then of course
there are people who are trying to
figure out how can we tackle this now
than the human side but on the side of
the allergen you know obviously there
have been a lot more accommodations as
of like to make foods more allergy
friendly for kids and then there are
ideas about how to prevent allergies
from manifesting in the first place so
changing the habits around what you know
pregnant people are told to eat what
lactating people are told to eat just
making sure those exposures are
happening early
um you know there are some people
looking into whether it's actually
really beneficial to have a pet in your
home when you have a really little kid
um you know to obviously not overuse
antibiotics but I think a lot of things
both on the treatment side and the
prevention side
it's been a pleasure talking allergies
with you thank you so much for uh
bringing Calvin and Hobbes into our
world delighted to be here as always uh
I am a cat fan so anytime you want me
back just say the word cat
foreign
depends a lot on our pets a lot a lot a
lot and yes most of the team are cat
people to be honest although I will
voice my doggy descent here so to
contribute to the academy of noise that
little Hobbs made earlier I bring you
Zuko the fiery red Tabby and owner of
shortwave co-host Emily Kwong if you
like the microphone
Kiki editor Gabriel Spitzer's feline
companion
baby owner producer Margaret cerino and
lastly
the cat who runs the whole show and also
our senior supervising editor Giselle
Grayson Pele
this episode was produced by Abby Levine
and Margaret and baby it was edited by
Giselle and Pele Brit Hansen checked the
facts the audio engineer was Stu
Rushfield Brendan Crump is our podcast
coordinator our senior director of
programming is Beth Donovan and the
senior vice president of programming is
Anya grundman I'm Erin Scott thanks as
always for listening to shortwave from
NPR
cover and covered in Hobbs are both big
fellows you want to say hi
[Music]
rude you ever do anything I tell you