NPR
[Music]
the indicator from Planet Money I'm
Darren woods and today I'm joined by one
of my favorite people from The Wider
Planet Money Universe Sarah Gonzalez
welcome to the show you're one of my
favorite people Darian Dean
and you're here for indicators of the
week I'm feeling it I'm ready all right
we've got two indicators today one is
about FTX a giant cryptocurrency
exchange that just filed for bankruptcy
and how the stock market reacts to
midterm elections that's all coming up
after the break
foreign
this message comes from NPR sponsor
fundrise a platform that makes investing
in high-end real estate easy utel
fundrise your investing goals and
fundrise puts your money into the real
estate deals that are right for you sign
up for free at fundrise.com indicator
all right Darian you're up first with
this like major crypto exchange that is
basically imploding right now where do
we start yeah so so my indicator is 32
billion dollars big indicator that's
huge it's the amount of value that has
disappeared from FTX earlier this year
investors were valuing it at 32 billion
and now one of the Venture Capital firms
that invested is valuing it at zero
dollars 32 billion to zero dollars yes
holy moly okay I have to admit I had not
actually ever heard
FTX until this week that might be true
but a lot of people heard about FDX in
the Super Bowl oh they had a commercial
of course I call it the wheel got a
stone wheel what does it do it it rules
yeah it's not as a bagel okay a bagel
you can eat
Larry David here Shilling for crypto
it's like an expensive commercial yeah I
mean they were riding high at the time
but their fortunes have kind of Fallen
back to Earth this week so FDX froze
uses withdrawals and that has shaken up
the crypto World in general the
protagonist is Sam bankman freed and he
goes by SPF the FTX guy goes by SBF okay
so anyways Sam bankman freed he's a 30
year old guy with a mop of hair he wears
shorts a lot he's really Earnest and
he's kind of been seen as the good guy
in crypto even though he was worth an
estimated 15 billion dollars before this
week it go to Washington DC and it Lobby
in support of more regulation of
cryptocurrencies here he is testifying
at a senate hearing earlier this year I
agree I would love to see the cftc play
a more active role in uh licensing and
regulating the digested space and I
agree that that will likely and he's
been giving a lot of interviews he
seemed super transparent about what he
was doing and including with NPR's David
gura in June about how he could even
step in when other crypto companies were
facing trouble I do feel like we have a
responsibility to seriously consider
stopping in even if it's at a loss to
ourselves
um to spread contagion and even if we
weren't the ones who caused it or were
involved in it and to understand and
what went wrong this week you need to
know that he has businesses in two
separate categories an exchange and a
trading firm so the exchange is FTX
which at its heart is just meant to be a
Matchmaker it matches crypto buyers with
crypto sellers like the stock exchange
and then on the other side SPF also
founded a crypto trading firm and that
is a company called Alameda research and
Alameda research borrowed and speculated
and tried to make money in crypto and in
theory this is still legal okay so you
have this like boring exchange as one
company and then the more risky money
maker on the other side two separate
companies yeah but SBF is heavily
involved with both okay and it's been
reported that several months ago Alameda
research made some bets that went badly
so I needed to borrow some money and
there's been reports from the Wall
Street Journal that it borrowed around
10 billion dollars from FTX oh so he
borrowed from his other company yeah
okay and that shouldn't have happened
the way it did where did FDX get that
eight billion dollars from well part of
it happened from the accounts of
everyday people just using fgx to buy
and sell crypto oh okay you know in the
everyday banking world this kind of
thing would not be allowed but to make
matters worse there was this problem
with the collateral that Alameda
research used to borrow the money so you
know collateral you often use when you
borrow money like maybe a house if
you're getting a home loan right so the
bank can just like take your house if
you don't pay back your loan right yeah
and in this case Alameda research is
collateral was a token issued by FTX so
the whole thing was just kind of a snake
eating its tail it wasn't very useful
collateral whatsoever it keeps getting
sketchier and sketchier exactly so it
was all just based on confidence and and
then once that confidence started to you
know disappear a little bit then
everything kind of collapsed and so SBF
called out for help from his former
Mentor Chung ping Zhao or actually likes
to be called CZ and he is the CEO of the
largest crypto exchange binance and
these two people don't always get along
like for one thing he is not a fan of
more crypto regulation like SPF is okay
and on Tuesday SBF announced that cz's
company binance was looking into bailing
out FDX but then the next day on
Wednesday CZ backed out of the deal he
said quote the issues are beyond our
control or ability to help wow brutal
pretty honest and that day it was
reported the Security and Exchange
Commission and the Department of Justice
were investigating FDX not to mention
more overseas investigations and this
morning FTX and Alameda research were
filing for bankruptcy and SBF resigned
as fdx's CEO oh my gosh it just keeps
getting worse so overall looking at this
yes it's been pretty fascinating to
watch this 32 billion dollars go up in
flames and this huge Fall From Grace for
SPF and big picture I mean this could be
the spark for what SBF was kind of
asking for all along stronger regulation
of crypto yeah exactly yes yes so it
could look more like regular financial
markets in the future and regular
financial markets are what you're going
to discuss take us away okay yeah I want
to focus on the standard stock market
especially after a midterm election so
my indicator I'm playing a little fast
and loose with it here but it is four as
in the midterm elections which happen
every four years got it a little bit of
a stretch but the midterms and the stock
market have this like pretty consistent
serious long-term relationship going on
okay is a ring involved so usually after
a midterm election the market goes up
this is pretty pretty well documented
it's pretty consistent since the year
1950 after every single midterm election
the market does a lot better no matter
which party wins no matter which party
is in power so is there is it like a
rational reason for this yeah so the
midterms generally are when there's like
a big shift in who controls the house
and the Senate right so typically
whoever is president during a midterm
election their party
does really poorly right the other party
ends up taking control of one or both
houses or keeping control if they
already had it so there's this split
government so for example like if the
House and Senate are both controlled by
Republicans but the president is
Democrat that's a split government or if
the House and Senate are split that's
considered a split Congress and the
stock market apparently really loves a
split government wow maybe the only part
of society that loves a Congress that
can't get anything done yeah right and
it is because the stock market sort of
gets like reassured that no big policy
changes no big spending is going to go
through in the next two years because
basically nothing happens when there's a
split government right when there's
gridlock it's a bit of a breather yeah
when there's gridlock no one can pass
any laws and so there's a lot less
uncertainty which of course the market
loves and okay that's starting to make
sense
um now at the moment we still don't know
the final results right it's so too
close to call but I do want to say that
all of this is just kind of like
historically speaking right all of this
might not actually mean a whole lot this
year just because there's so much going
on right now we had historic spending
because of the pandemic High inflation
High interest rates that the Federal
Reserve says needs to stay high people
are worried about a recession there's
Russia's war in Ukraine all of this will
affect the stock market though so like
who knows uh an interesting thing is
that like a certain split is apparently
more Market friendly and it is when
there is a republican Congress under a
Democrat president that is apparently
the best environment for stocks thank
you so much for joining into guys of the
week Sarah yeah of course thanks Darian
this episode was produced by senior
producer via lay with engineering from
Robert Rodriguez Dylan Sloan checked the
facts cake and Cannon edits the show and
the indicator is a production of NPR