NPR
[Music]
the brightest flashlight app was
developed for something very simple this
was during the time when a lot of
Android phones didn't have built-in
flashlights like the iPhone so this app
would turn on all the available lights
essentially making the phone into a
flashlight but the brightest flashlight
was also doing something else it was
recording users locations and sending
that information to advertisers and this
landed the company in hot water with the
Federal Trade Commission that was almost
a decade ago since then the market for
location data has continued to flourish
it is a multi-billion dollar industry
where information on people's precise
whereabouts is still being collected for
mobile apps and sold to companies or
government agencies often without users
knowledge or direct consent
this is the indicator from Planet Money
I'm Waylon Wong and I'm Darian woods
today on the show we're going to look at
Mobile location data how it's gathered
sold and used and we're going to talk to
One developer about his experience to
try to build a weather app that takes
privacy seriously
support for this podcast comes from NPR
sponsor Raymond James a firm focused on
transforming lives businesses and
communities through tailored wealth
management banking and capital markets
Solutions learn more at raymondjames.com
our phones contain a treasure Trove of
information about us what we're watching
buying searching for and where we are
precise geolocation data is really your
longitude and your latitude so exactly
where you are like you are in your
living room in your apartment Lena Gomez
a privacy lawyer a couple of years ago
she helped launch a watchdog group that
investigated mobile apps this was also
when more investigative journalism was
coming out about the industry like in
2020 Vice reported that the U.S military
was buying location data collected from
a variety of apps usually what happens
is that apps are collecting information
about you the apps then turn around and
sell that information to data Brokers
third parties who then package that data
repurpose it and then sell it to
anyone that wants to buy the data later
says location data can be helpful like
say an epidemiologist wants to track the
spread of infectious diseases in a
population or a real estate company
might want to analyze foot traffic
patterns when deciding where to open a
store and then there are apps that
simply wouldn't work without knowing
their users locations think of
navigation and mapping apps or ride
sharing apps like Lyft and Uber so it's
not all nefarious and bad but
unfortunately the way that it's been
used today has exploited individuals
because this information is really
sensitive one high profile example from
last year involved a Catholic priest he
resigned after a new site claimed to
have linked his phone with data showing
that he had visited gay bars and used
the location-based dating app grinder
and location data came under renewed
scrutiny after Roe v Wade was overturned
Congress is investigating privacy
concerns related to period tracking apps
and how they collect data including
location
and in August the FTC sued a data broker
named kochava it said the company's data
could be used to track people visiting
sensitive places like reproductive
health clinics and domestic violence
shelters so how does location data get
from an app to a data broker to
companies that are paying for this
information Lena says that often the app
developers have no idea that this data
is being collected in the first place
and that's because of something called
software development kits or sdks
basically they're pieces of code that
app developers use when creating an App
instead of writing the code from scratch
so think about making spaghetti you
could spend hours simmering a complex
bolognese sauce on the stove or you
could buy a jar of pre-made sauce and
get dinner on the table in 15 minutes
yeah so sdks are these pre-made Jarred
pasta sources of the mobile app industry
they contain pre-made software for
functions like taking credit card
payments or sending instant messages so
sdks can be very useful but unbeknownst
to app developers some SDK creators
insert location tracking capabilities
into their software and sell that data
to Brokers what happens a lot of time is
that the SDK has what we call invisible
code and the code can then extract your
location information and the app
developers actually sometimes don't even
know that they're putting this into the
app some developers choose to avoid sdks
altogether for this very reason
developers like Brian Mueller I'm Brian
Mueller and I'm the founder of carrot
weather this uh snarky little weather
app that has this personality built into
it I'm sick of these vanilla weather
apps yeah well if you want a weather app
kind of spicing up your life carrot
weather might be your thing because okay
every time you open this app you are
greeted with a rude message like if it's
sunny and warm carrot might say I hope
you get a horrible sunburn this is quite
the app I don't know why people would
want this in their life but maybe I
don't know self-flagellation is a thing
maybe just to feel alive does it feel
alive you know I have learned that
carrots personality is pretty acerbic
and it's sometimes bordering on
homicidal but one thing that carrot does
not do despite being a weather app is
collect and store precise location data
a few few years ago when Brian started
reading about how invisible code could
be lurking inside sdks he decided to
remove them from his app he also doesn't
sell ads because he didn't want to
expose his customers data to third-party
advertising companies I remember joking
that carrot wants your location data so
that she can use it to like send an
assassin after you not not give it to
someone else to Market stuff to you so
one challenge for Brian is that he has
to rely on third party weather data
providers you know like the companies
that actually do the forecasts and he
can't control what those companies do
with his customers data so he's built a
couple of safeguards for example he puts
his own servers in between his customers
and the weather data providers that way
those companies don't see his customers
IP addresses they only see requests
coming from Brian's servers and another
thing that I do is uh my request to the
weather data providers don't use the
most precise GPS coordinates I round
those coordinates up so that they'll
never be able to like say that this user
is at this specific address Brian says
though as a consumer he personally
doesn't mind his location being used for
targeted ads and this is a pretty common
mindset like our online experience can
be more tailored to our interests
because of the information that we
provide to apps and advertisers and ads
are what enables so many apps and
services to be free but the conversation
station around how sensitive personal
information gets used is prompting
people like Brian to take a hard look at
the trade-offs between privacy
convenience and in his case making a
living as an app developer there's so
many cases out there where location data
can be used
to really hurt people
and that's the kind of stuff that I
don't want to contribute to both Brian
and Lena say that because the US doesn't
have a federal Privacy Law like Europe's
gdpr law it's largely been left up to
individual companies and developers to
figure out their own policies Apple for
example introduced privacy features last
year that let iPhone users opt out of
getting tracked by advertisers privacy
Advocates applauded the features but
those changes also resulted in billions
of lost dollars in ad revenue and sales
for companies and for individual people
like Lena the wild west nature of the
mobile app industry means that she has
to stay personally Vigilant not only for
herself but her parents too who aren't
as tech savvy as she is I look at their
phone and I'm like do you really need
these apps what's like the most random
app you found on your parents phone
where you're like no you don't need this
my mom had this like flower of the day
app
night I was like what is this and she
was like I don't know look nice I was
like you don't need this
well the sunflower might look nice but
you can also get insulted by a really
mean weather app if you want who
wouldn't want that 24 000 people are
killed by lightning every year will you
be one of them
well that estimate sounds a little high
but I wouldn't dare contradict carrot
she will come for me I would know that
she knows where you live maybe not the
address but where you live generally
this episode was produced by Nikki
Willette with engineering by Catherine
Silva Dylan Sloan checked the facts via
laser senior producer Kate and Kennon
edits the show and the indicator is a
production of NPR
[Music]
[Applause]