NPR
[Music]
this is the indicator from Planet Money
I'm Darian Woods I'm Waylon Wong and it
is jobs Friday
love jumps Friday all the
new jobs report is out today and it's
that the U.S economy added 261 000 jobs
in October the unemployment rate Rose
slightly to 3.7 percent but there's
still 1.9 jobs for every one unemployed
person some of these jobs are ones that
businesses have trouble filling with
American workers even when they
advertise widely or raise wages and a
potential solution for this hiring
shortfall is immigration now there are
lots of ways foreign workers come to the
U.S one of them is a Visa program that
businesses from vacation resorts to
Seafood processors rely on to staff
their busy seasons
today on the show we will learn about
this program with the potential to
alleviate Staffing shortages and we look
at new economic research that shows when
businesses hire foreign workers through
this program they end up actually
creating new jobs for Americans
[Music]
for years temperate temporary foreign
workers have been coming to the U.S for
months at a time to process salmon in
Alaska and pick crabs in Maryland they
clean hotel rooms and work in the
kitchens of ski resorts in the winter
and beach resorts in the summer a lot of
them also work in groundskeeping and
Forestry Economist Michael Clemens is a
senior fellow at the center for Global
development where he studies migration
and Michael says that evidence of
temporary foreign workers is all around
us if you see a right-of-way through the
forest for utility lines somebody needs
to clear the vegetation From Below those
so the forest doesn't come back if
there's a pulp paper Forest somebody
needs to go in a remote area and do the
difficult physical labor of planting all
those seedlings many of these workers
have what are called h2b visas this is a
Visa program that hires temporary
foreign workers without college degrees
for non-agricultural jobs every year the
US government hands out 66 000 h2b visas
split between the winter and the summer
the workers hail from country countries
like Mexico Guatemala Jamaica Serbia and
the Philippines and the h-2b Visa was
almost not to be for nearly seven
decades starting in 1885 the U.S banned
foreign workers without advanced
education but in 1952 The post-world War
II Labor Market had a lot of jobs and
not enough workers and that's when the
h-2b Visa was created it was designed to
be a way to hire foreign workers when
there was literally no other option in
other words when businesses couldn't
find any American workers to take a job
at that wage
but lawmakers were concerned that
foreign workers would replace their
American counterparts so they put in
restrictions that remain in place today
for example the h-2b jobs have to be
limited in time like seasonal or one-off
work and employers have to certify with
the government that no American is
willing and able to do the job the
Department of Labor can ask for evidence
of recruitment activities did you
advertise in newspapers did you
advertise on the radio when people came
to you through the State Workforce
agency saying I'm unemployed I would
like to work in speed food processing
what happened to them Michael points out
that these kinds of jobs can't or
haven't been automated and they're also
jobs that don't attract American workers
even at higher wages so remember when we
said that there's a yearly cap on h2b
visas of 66 000. well that limit was put
in place in 1990 when there were far
fewer h2b workers in the country around
20 000 workers so the cap of 66 000
seemed really generous at that time that
number was seen as so high that it would
never be reached well the number was
reached and then some in 2019 employers
requested triple the number of h2b visas
available for half a year by 2022 the
number of requests was four times the
quota and the government's tried some
stop Gap measures like in the law they
are allowed to extend the number of
visas by up to around 65 000 extra visas
and that's all they're going to do in
the coming year but whether a business
gets these visas depends a lot on luck
this is because when employers submit
their request to the Department of Labor
they get randomly assigned a letter of
the alphabet A through e the applicants
in the a group get evaluated first the
ones that don't get letter a end up
hiring about half as many as they would
otherwise prefer to it's not bigger
firms or smaller firms more productive
less productive it's it's literally just
the luck of the draw last month Michael
and Othello
businesses that won and lost the 2021
lottery for h2b visas and here's what
they found businesses that were able to
hire foreign workers the winners
produced 17 percent more stuff than the
losers the winners also spent triple the
amount on investing in their business in
other words just being able to hire h2b
workers unlocked productivity not just
for the foreign workers coming in but
for the entire company and Michael says
businesses that are expanding tend to
create more jobs for Americans if a
restaurant can operate because there is
a dishwasher that means not just more
jobs for people waiting tables it also
means more jobs for the accountants who
keep the books of the restaurant it
means more jobs for the people at the
businesses from which things are bought
by the owner of the restaurant with the
revenue they get because the restaurant
can operate because there is a
dishwasher there are all kinds of Ripple
effects Michael's analysis found that
businesses who couldn't hire h2b workers
their losers weren't able to to hire
American workers for the unfilled
positions either and the result was that
these businesses output and investment
fell industries that rely on h2b Visa
workers have shared anecdotes that align
with Michael's findings for example a
national landscape or organization said
this year that in past Seasons their
members have had to turn away customers
and cancel equipment purchases because
they didn't have enough hdb workers in
Colorado the Aspen skiing company used
to employ hundreds of hdb workers at its
four ski areas that was over a decade
ago last year it got approved for only a
couple of dozen h2p visas it is a little
nerve-wracking because you never know if
the government is going to approve you
to to have the amount that you've
requested that's Michaela Ford the
company's acting director of talent
acquisition she says the companies had
to get creative about seasonal Staffing
it has an arrangement with a hotel in
Colorado Springs that high hires h2b
workers for the summer season when the
summer ends those workers pack up and
head over to Aspen for the winter these
h-2b workers are known as in-country
extensions and this winter 55 of them
will be at Aspen skiing company Michaela
says she feels good about this year's
Staffing levels and one big benefit of
having enough workers for the peak
season we all get a go ski powder
seriously though we do get to take you
know ski breaks and for fully staffed if
we're understaffed you know that means
we're asking somebody maybe to stay
longer or to work an extra shift and
that can really weigh on someone it can
really impact a business and so that's
really why we do these Visa programs I
would love my brakes to be ski breaks
how do I sign up you got to relocate to
Aspen that's true and it's also not all
ski breaks and sunshine for these
seasonal workers many h2b workers
perform difficult physically demanding
jobs and they're often in these
precarious situations where they can't
speak up about unsafe conditions or
mistreatment you know their visas are
tied to their employer they also don't
have a pathway to citizenship in the US
Michael Clemens says the h2b Visa
program has needed improvements
basically since it was conceived but
progress has been stalled in the absence
of broader immigration reform it's
really hard to find somebody who will
put H2 visas on a bumper sticker and say
I love H2 visas that doesn't change the
fact that for several sectors that are
crucial for all of us foreign
fundamental workers are a major
constraint and this is the policy tool
that we have in order to give massive
opportunities to them and substantial
opportunities to American workers and to
the rest of the economy honk if you love
learning about the labor market that's
what's on my bumper sticker
um it's gonna sell well how do I buy in
let me get the printing press ready
foreign
this episode was produced by Nikki
Willett and engineered by Catherine
Silva Noah Glick checked the facts via
laser senior producer Kate and Cannon
edits the show and the indicator is a
production of NPR
[Music]