NPR
[Music]
this is the integrated from Planet Money
I'm Darian woods and I'm Patty Hirsch at
the heart of every piece of Machinery
powered by electricity lies The Humble
magnet of course you know this from your
physics class at high school Darian
right oh yeah I was at the front row
anyway most magnets like the one in your
battery powered clock for example are
cheap and easy to produce but the
magnets in high-tech Machinery like
electric vehicle Motors or I don't know
space shuttle turbines are very
different these so-called permanent
magnets are subject to intense heat and
pressure and to make the really high-end
ones you need a special ingredient rare
Earths these are elements that can be
hard to find and are even harder to
extract and refine yeah and the vast
majority of rare Earths right now are
produced in China which means that China
dominates that market recently however
scientists discovered a way to produce a
metal in a lab that could be used to
make high-end magnets without using rare
Earths the metal is called tetratanite
and on today's show we're going to find
out what it is how it's made and how it
came from space that's right and we're
going to hear how it could transform not
just the market for rare Earths and
permanent magnets but the balance of
technological power between China and
the West that's all coming up after the
break
[Music]
support for this podcast comes from NPR
sponsor Raymond James a firm focused on
transforming lives businesses and
communities through tailored wealth
management banking and capital markets
Solutions learn more at Raymond
james.com
to understand all about tetraonite we
called up one of the scientists who
helped make it in the lab I am Laura
Henderson Lewis I am a professor of
mechanical engineering and chemical
engineering at Northeastern University
in Boston Massachusetts we also called
an investor who tracks technologies that
use rare Earths my name is Jonathan
hikaway and I'm the president of
stormcrow capital limited Jonathan is
tremendously excited by the news that
scientists may have found a way to
create a metal that could remove the
need to use rare Earths in some high-end
magnets this new discovery this this
tetrotainite announcement is one of the
most interesting things I've seen in the
space
and I look at a dozen of these sorts of
discoveries a week
99.9 of them will never become
commercial this one actually might
tejate Knight is not an unknown medal
but Laura says it is pretty
extraordinary tetrotenai is a cosmic
mineral
and it was first discovered and named in
the 1980s and when Laura says
tetrotainite is Cosmic she means that in
its natural form it literally comes from
isospace it's only found in a few
meteorites some of them are in the
Smithsonian it's made out of two common
Metals iron and nickel which bonded and
cooled over a very very long time while
the meteorite was spinning around up
there in the cosmos and that doesn't
happen very quickly naturally so it
could take up to you know many millions
up to a billion years to form a large
piece of tetrotaini at replicating a
billion year cooling process in a lab is
challenging and perhaps not surprisingly
rather expensive I mean good luck
getting a lease for that length of time
yeah but Jonathan hike away says the
benefits are potentially huge that's
because iron a nickel are dirt cheap
compared to rare Earths like neodymium
or terbium that we currently need to use
when we make high performance permanent
magnets today neodymium oxide is true
trading at about a hundred dollars it's
a hundred and four dollars a kilo
terbium oxide which is one of the
materials that allows magnets made with
it to function at much higher
temperatures than it normally would
that's trading at something like one
thousand nine hundred dollars a kilogram
but nickel and iron on the other hand
trade for less than 25 bucks a kilogram
so you can see the cost saving
implications here if we can make
permanent magnets out of such
inexpensive materials it's got the
possibility and the potential of of
actually crippling the existing Rare
Earth Market crippling well that's you
heard it here first watch out Rare Earth
Market Yan rarests are expensive not
because they're difficult to mine
although some are the problem is that
they're usually combined with other
materials and it's the process of
separating them to get that raw element
that's so difficult you dig The Ore out
of the ground
you you grind it you beneficiate it you
pull out those Rare earth-bearing
Minerals you subject them to an acid
leech to pull the metals out getting the
individual rare it's out is extremely
difficult the US used to be a leader in
the rare Earth's business back in the
1980s but Laura says that production was
so expensive and so messy that the US
decided to Outsource to China So Not
only was China blessed with a large
deposit of rare Earth elements it's in
inner Mongolia
uh but they were also willing to put in
the infrastructure
to separate these elements and the U.S
was not so particularly interested uh in
doing that especially if China would do
it for a reduced overhead because the
processing is not particularly
environmentally friendly the 30 years
old Jonathan says China effectively owns
the rare Earth's Market almost all of
the processing and quantity in terms of
separating out pure neodymium oxide pure
prasodemium oxide or a mix of the two
that's pure enough to be used in magnets
is done in China almost all of the
conversion of those oxide materials to
Metals is done in China and a very large
proportion of the actual magnet alloy
manufacturing is done in China China
controls more than 71 percent of the
world's extraction and 87 percent of the
world's processing capacity of rare
Earths it also makes more than 80
percent of the world's permanent magnets
Jonathan says that if tetratayanite is a
viable success most permanent magnets
could be produced at a fraction of their
current cost that would turn the magnet
Market on its head and also the market
in rare Earths this is going to be a
fairly big disruption to a lot of
companies the the Chinese companies or
the producers are going to have to start
worrying about
what their economics are going to look
like if they're only selling a fraction
of the amount that they used to the
magnets that go into your electric
scooter or your air conditioner would be
cheaper which would be a win for
consumers but there could be a big
downside some rare Earths could end up
becoming more expensive because it would
be less incentive to mine and extract
them and that could be a problem for a
range of other Industries and that's
because rare Earths aren't only used in
magnet manufacturing they're also key
components and all kinds of high-tech
applications from fiber optics to
radiation scanners to Advanced military
equipment if suddenly the rare earth
industry can't afford to dig the
material out of the ground because we
can't sell magnet materials the
availability of things like luticium
erbium for the fiber optic industry and
some of these other small quantity quite
rare rare it's
is going to suffer as a result and these
markets aren't huge the rare Earth's
Market is somewhere between 12 and 16
billion dollars a year and just for
scale that is about the size of the
global market for gin oh really
permanent magnets that's about 34
billion which is about the size of the
global market for orange juice somewhat
less interesting so the disruption of
either the magnets Market or the rare
Earth's Market wouldn't hurt China that
much financially but strategically it's
a whole other question the demand for a
high-end permanent magnets is growing
fast and these magnets are vital to all
sorts of products that are going to
become increasingly important as the
world transitions to a clean energy
economy so of course I'm talking about
things like electric vehicles industrial
air conditioners and wind turbines and
so it's in China's interest to stay on
top of the markets and magnets and rare
Earths and the US knows it and that's
why there's been talk about America
moving back into the rare Earth's
business but the us only has one mine
running at the moment that's in
California yeah and bringing new
facilities online will take years which
makes the lab production of tetrotainite
look kind of like a gift of magical
alien technology from outer space which
it sort of is just without the aliens
but Laura Lewis at Northeastern says
it's no quick fix having this is not the
same as having a magnet I often use the
analogy you may have a material to make
a brick
but you have to put the bricks together
to make a wall and then that wall makes
the Taj Mahal she says there's no
guarantee that the lab tattoo night will
work as well as the tiny bits of metal
mine from the meteorites even if it does
nothing will happen overnight yeah best
case she says it could be five to eight
years before Tetra tonight could make a
meaningful difference to the magnet
production business or to The Rare Earth
Markets until then the race is on to
compete with China and to secure new
sources of rare Earths far in the
Australian desert deep under the seabed
in Japan
maybe in outer space yeah I mean once
you've run out of land that's my guess
as we have to go it is the final
frontier it is after all the final
frontier
this show was produced by Noah Glick
with engineering from Maggie Luthor
Dylan Sloan checked the facts via Leia's
our senior producer cake and Cannon
edits the show and the indicator is a
production of NPR
visit meteorite or meteoroid fatty so
here's the thing when it's in space it's
a meteoroid okay when it hits the
atmosphere and it burns you've got that
shooting star thing that's a meteor and
if it survives that and it hits the
earth that is a meteorite