NPR
[Music]
is the indicator from Planet Money I'm
Waylon Wong and I'm Darian Woods the
debate over how to curb gun violence in
the US has arrived at the doorstep of
the financial industry and more
specifically companies linked to credit
cards within all the infrastructure that
undergirds the credit card industry
there is one little piece of it that has
gotten thrust into this conversation and
it is called the merchant category code
gun control Advocates believe the
merchant category code could be an
important tool in identifying suspicious
gun sales but getting retailers plus
other players in the credit card
industry to use this tool is another
thing today on the show we zoom in in on
this humble bit of financial Plumbing to
see how it works and why it's getting
the spotlight and the gun violence
debate
support for this podcast comes from NPR
sponsor Raymond James a firm focused on
transforming lives businesses and
communities through tailored wealth
management banking and capital markets
Solutions learn more at raymondjames.com
in 2018 Andrew Ross Sulkin got curious
about something he's a economist and
editor at large at the New York Times
where he covers the financial industry
after the school shooting in Parkland
Florida in February of that year Andrew
started thinking where the gunman in
mass shootings getting the money for
their guns it started with a hunch that
people couldn't afford to buy all of
these guns in paraphernalia
without the financing element the credit
piece from a credit card Andrew started
digging and found that a significant
number of Shooters did use credit cards
the gunman behind the Pulse Nightclub
attack in 2016 for example charged over
twenty thousand dollars in weapons on
multiple credit cards and what stood out
to Andrea was that before carrying out
the attack the gunman had Googled terms
like credit card unusual spending and
why Banks stopped your purchases to me
that was proof positive
that the banks and the credit card
system were in fact financing these
shootings there was no other way to
think about it and the financial system
already uses data and sophisticated
algorithms to detect illegal activities
like fraud and money laundering so
Andrew thought what if there was a way
to identify suspicious spending activity
at gun stores now credit card companies
and Banks don't collect product level
data on what specific items people are
buying with their cards but the one
thing that is communicated back to all
of those folks
is the merchant category code the
merchant category code so let's talk
about what this is the merchant category
code or MCC for short is a four digit
number that's used to categorize a
business by what they primarily sell
that could be cat food or concert
tickets or refrigerator repair and the
industry uses these Merchant category
codes in a few different ways one
example is reward programs you know like
credit cards that give you double points
for your groceries you get those points
when you use your card at a business
that is categorized as a grocery store
another way the industry uses these
codes is to gather data on consumer
spending David shipper is a strategic
advisor at a Financial Services Research
firm called it navarica group Merchant
category of codes really help to Define
volume and see where things are moving
in different types of or lines of
business like grocery department stores
hotels I mean without them it really
would be difficult to understand as a
card issuer where your consumers are
spending money Merchant category codes
have been around since 2003 and they're
managed by a group in Geneva Switzerland
called the okay are you ready for this
name Darian I'm ready they're called The
International Organization for
standardization standardization so like
no free expression Allowed no not at all
but really the iso is the authority that
approves or rejects requests for new
codes based on criteria like is the
proposed new category distinct enough
from the categories that already exist
and do the businesses in the category
generate at least 10 million dollars in
annual sales so this Swiss organization
maintains the list of codes and then the
codes are assigned to businesses by
Banks and here's how that works let's
say I'm opening a new Candy Shop in my
town and I want to accept credit cards I
need to open an account with a bank that
can handle those transactions for me the
bank will ask me what's your primary
line of business and I'll say candy so
the Bank assigns me the merchant
category code for candy nuts and
confectionary stores and if I were to
pursue my true dream which is to open a
wig store there is a specific code just
for Wig and dupe stores believe it or
not there is also one for snowmobile
dealers or this is one of my favorites
detective agencies and security services
including armored cars and guard dogs so
these category codes can get pretty
specific even so until September there
wasn't a code specifically for stores
that sell guns and ammunition those
businesses are usually designated as
Sporting Goods or miscellaneous and
Andrew Ross Sorkin thought what if there
was a new code just for gun stores so
the financial industry could have a
chance at potentially spotting
suspicious activity so in 2018 he
started writing and giving talks about
this idea and One bank took notice
Amalgamated Bank it submitted an
application to the iso and Switzerland
for a new Merchant category code and
after an initial rejection the iso
approved the request and David said that
caused quite a stir I would say this is
probably the first time MCC codes have
ever made news wow big day for MCC codes
I know yeah the big win the new code was
considered a win by gun control
Advocates but a Firearms trade
Association and almost two dozen
Republican Attorneys General are bulking
at the idea saw some lawmakers at a
recent Congressional hearing with bank
CEOs representative Roger Williams of
Texas said the new code is an invasion
of privacy anyone who is against the
rights of gun owners will want your
institutions to flag every single
transaction with a gun MCC to law
enforcement David says that it's not
clear how effect of the new Merchant
category code will actually be as a way
to spot suspicious purchases for
starters the code is like a blunt
instrument it only identifies the type
of business where a credit card is used
it doesn't give any information about
what was purchased so if you think
about a you know gun and ammunition
store if you go there and you purchase a
hunting bow
the MCC code is not going to know that
you purchased that versus a shotgun it's
not going to know that you purchased
ammunition versus maybe you purchased a
lot of candy and then there's the
question of whether the new Merchant
category code will get used at all so
remember we mentioned earlier that Banks
assign the codes to the businesses and
gun stores are usually designated as
Sporting Goods or miscellaneous so for
this new code to actually get used
stores and their Banks would have to
work together to reclassify the store
David says he doesn't really see that
happening and he's also skeptical that
newly opened gun stores will want this
code assigned to them and meanwhile the
big payment card networks visa and
MasterCard they responded to the
controversy by saying they respect the
privacy of their cardholders the
companies said they do not track
personal purchasing habits nor do they
block legal transactions based on
Merchant category codes
Visa said it doesn't think these codes
can or should be used to track purchases
like gun sales the company even said we
do not believe private companies should
serve as moral Arbiters so at the moment
the new Merchant category code exists
but it needs financial institutions to
embrace it and both David and Andrew see
ways that people can avoid getting their
transactions flagged like they could
just switch to cash but Andrew says he
hopes the new code will inspire
continued debate and reflection in the
financial industry about how those
businesses can help reduce gun violence
this episode was produced by Corey
Bridges with engineering from Maggie
luthar was fact-checked by Catherine
Yang and Dylan Sloan Viet Lisa senior
producer taking Cannon edits the show
and the indicator is a production of NPR
foreign