NPR
[Music]
today the 12 members of what's known as
the Federal Open Market Committee or the
fomc made a big decision good afternoon
my colleagues and I are strongly
committed chair Jerome Powell announced
the fomc had decided to raise interest
rates three quarters of a percentage
point today and interest rates can be
suffocating for a lot of people
mortgages are more expensive car loans
and credit cards get harder to pay off
businesses stop hiring the overall
effect is designed to slow down the
economy to tackle inflation and instead
of debating whether the 12 members of
the fomc are making the right or the
wrong decisions
there's another way we could be
reimagining the feds work all together
we could be putting interest rates on
autopilot with the basic formula that a
high schooler could memorize the guide
is pretty simple when they followed it
has worked pretty well when they haven't
followed it it's not worked so well
Stanford economist John Taylor is
talking about his creation the Taylor
rule this is the indicator from Planet
Money I'm Darian woods and I'm Mary
Childs the Taylor rule is a disarmingly
simple equation that could tell central
banks how much to raise or lower
interest rates but recently the FED has
strayed from this rule Today's Show what
it is and whether or not it could be
better than expert human judgment
support for this podcast comes from NPR
sponsor Raymond James a firm focused on
transforming lives businesses and
communities through tailored wealth
management banking and capital markets
Solutions learn more at raymondjames.com
the Taylor rule is a Formula that can
automate how much to raise or lower
interest rates to keep inflation steady
and its Origins start in the 1970s back
then American monetary policy was a mess
inflation was out of control and
unemployment was high even more
fundamentally it was unclear how a
central bank should do Central Bank
things like the fed's Dual mandate the
core goal of keeping both prices stable
and Employment High that didn't even
exist until 1977. in the 70s everything
was up for debate John Taylor was an
economist then recently out of his PhD
he was working at the Council of
economic advisors under President Ford
there were all sorts of Chaos in the 70s
we had money growth High money growth
low it didn't seem like the way we
should be conducting policies so I
started with how can we conduct policy
in a more understandable way John almost
looking for a way to guide fed officials
towards keeping the economy growing
steadily not too much inflation not too
much unemployment in other words he was
looking for a recipe for a soup that
wouldn't be too salty or too sweet but a
lot of the recipes out there giving
models for how the central banks should
raise or lower interest rates had a lot
of inputs and equations exchange rates
government deficits may be the number of
ships lining up at the ports John didn't
think these models would work for policy
makers gee this recipe is so complicated
can we simplify we want it to be
available for everybody not just the
sophisticated people who know about all
the ingredients in the taste so John
would take out one ingredient at a time
and see how the model held up and
keeping a hypothetical economy satiated
it may be see if he could replace two
variables as one like I don't know
instead of both consumption and
investment he could replace these with
GDP which covers the whole economy he
was boiling it down meanwhile at the FED
under chair Paul volcker Central Banking
got more clarity yes it had its dual
mandate to keep prices stable and jobs
plentiful but in reality it was focusing
much more on the keeping prices stable
part of its mandate keeping inflation
low but John still felt like the FED
could be much clearer about how it went
about its business and in 1992 John was
asked to give a talk at Carnegie Mellon
University on what he'd been cooking
over all these years and the recipe was
essentially this raise interest rates by
more than the spike in inflation
so we have this inflation Target for the
fed that's two percent so let's say you
have inflation bumbling along at two
percent but then one day it spikes up to
three percent then the Taylor rule says
that you would raise interest rates by
one and a half percentage points that's
more than that one percentage Point bump
in inflation that we've just had and
you'd also take into account how
overheated or undercooked The Wider
economy is as well and those two factors
together inflation and the state of the
economy that's more or less it that's
the Taylor rule I didn't think it'd be
so important or useful that's for sure
it was like hey let's try this but I
caught on quite quickly and it worked
pretty well that's all John crunched the
numbers for his Rule and he found that
it described fairly closely what the
Federal Reserve had actually done in the
1980s and would go on to do in the 1990s
these were times described as the great
moderation when inflation was low and
any recessions were mild and when the
FED had deviated from the Taylor rule
where it hadn't raised interest rates as
much as the rule suggested that was the
1970s when inflation got so high that
the FED had to crash the economy in the
early 80s to stamp it out it was also in
the early 2000s when low interest rates
contributed to massive housing price
growth fueling the speculative bubble
that led to the Great Recession in 2008.
John felt like his historical analysis
Vindicated the Taylor rule if the rule
had been followed maybe we could have
avoided those crashes and as the years
go on John is trying to promote this
idea we have an autopilot for the FED we
have policy rules and in his view policy
rules like the Taylor rule work better
than human judgment most of the time
here's John testifying in 2014 at the
house Financial Services committee it's
because of the success of policy rules
that I recommend that legislation be put
in place to require the FED to report on
its policy Rule and for the next few
years there were efforts in Congress to
pass bills that would encourage the FED
to follow a rule like the Taylor rule
one bill required the FED to get audited
for an explanation if they deviated but
the proposed bills face strong
resistance notably from Janet Yellen
chair of the FED at the time she thought
this breached Fair Independence I am
very opposed and have on the record is
saying I am very opposed to energetic
Yellen is speaking at Stanford
University in 2017. and John Taylor's in
the room and at first Janet Yellen is
complimentary consider first the
well-known Taylor rule we which embodies
key principles of good monetary policy
but you know what happens with a
compliment sandwich right the painful
stuff is in the middle exactly it's not
delicious Janet Yellen points out that
yes the formula is simple just plug in
inflation and where we are relative to
potential GDP but which indicators you
use for those matter a lot like do we
use the Consumer Price Index for
inflation or do we use the fed's
preferred consumption expenditures index
also Janet Yellen says that geopolitical
events like trade Wars might be on the
horizon things say only a committee of
human beings might be able to anticipate
Janet Yellen also gave evidence that the
Taylor rule just systematically gives
you interest rates that are too high it
doesn't take into account how shifts in
globalization and demographics have
pushed interest rates down overall in
the last few decades the Taylor rule for
this reason provides a problematic
benchmark the speech was a passionate
defense of human beings versus the
robotic formula of the Taylor rule and
the bill didn't pass but the FED did on
its own initiative start publishing
charts twice a year that showed what it
had been doing with interest rates and
compared that with the Taylor rule
and John says that has been insightful
in this pandemic economy under the
Taylor rule interest rates would have
risen to around seven or eight percent
last year
instead they stayed near zero I'd say
right now that most central banks are
still behind and it's not like they're
rushing to do this John is holding out
hope that our current High inflation
might revive interest in
institutionalizing his rule what you
have to say well look this worked pretty
well it looks like it'll work in the
future let's just do this and my My Hope
Is this experience will bring us more in
that direction rather than take us away
[Music]
Taylor's version of the world is a world
without human beings it's just a
mathematical formula yeah maybe he's
right maybe we're the problem wow
the show was produced by Brittany Cronin
with engineering by Maggie Luther it was
fact checked by Dylan Sloan via laser
senior producer and Kate and Cannon
edits the show the indicator is a
production of NPR